[Music]
let's talk
money hello and welcome to let's talk
money I'm your host surub upadhi it's
the middle of December which means it's
holiday season now many of you would
have already planned your travel and
vacations and those who haven't are
probably looking forward to booking
their first trip of 2025 early in the
New Year yes the travel bug has has
bitten us all and it's perhaps here to
stay so how can we plan smarter for our
travels in our holidays what are the
hottest destinations of 2025 and while
we research enough on the hotels and the
experiences that we want on that dream
trip do we pay enough attention to
travel insurance yes you got it it is
the travel special edition of let's talk
money and helping us plan our 2025
wonderlast better are moit Joi of
Skyscanner and priia deshmuk of IC
Lombard lady and gentlemen great to have
both of you on the show thank you very
much for joining in and I'm I don't know
if both of you have booked your trips or
if you're big travel Enthusiast yourself
moit Mo's joining us all the way from
London this morning
right yes hi good morning good morning
lovely to see you all Priya what about
you are you a big Avid traveler yourself
well I do travel and uh thank you for
having me on the show and uh you know
good morning to everybody all right uh
so you know we want to start with some
broad brush Trends on of uh you know
what the qualitative and quantitative
aspects tell us yes we know our friends
our family everyone's traveling more but
moit you tell us I mean you guys on
Skyscanner you're looking at all of
these searches all of these bookings uh
day in and day out so what has
2024 uh brought forward when it comes to
Indians
traveling yeah it's an exciting time for
travel at the moment 2024 was all about
cultural exploration so we saw a shift
in the traveler mindset moving from just
going to a new country to escape to
actually going there to immerse
themselves in the culture right from
Geek tripping which is going to see your
favorite artists perform somewhere to
actually going to some iconic landmarks
that they've seen on a TV show so we've
SE seen that shift in 2024 and moving on
to 2025 the desire for travel remains uh
really strong um 86% of Indian Travelers
want to spend the same or more um on
flights and 80% of Indian Travelers want
to spend the same or more on hotels
which shows there is a big big um
interest in travel for next year we've
also seen um some travel trends that
have come out through some number
crunching that we've done through a
survey that we've done um and then we've
highlighted seven travel Trends one of
them being sport mode which is
essentially traveling to see see your
favorite athlete or to support your
favorite team we've also looked at Art
Venture where there is a big focus on um
Indian Travelers wanting to go and
experience immersive art um reset jeters
which is another one which is all about
Wellness based traveling taking some
time off to disconnect that continues
from 2024 into
2025 and and then there are a few more
which talk about Astro Adventures which
is wanting to go and see the Aurora
Borealis the northern lights and tromo
and Norway has come out as one of the
trending destinations where you can go
and and see them and then there are a
few like game vacation we've seen a lot
of interest from Indian Travelers
wanting to go to location that they've
either played on a game or it also kind
of reflects on some esport events that
they want to go for and the last couple
being Horticulture um which is wanting
to um experience the the the cherry
blossoms and last the cowboy core which
is just having an experience of a
farmhouse day so that's the various
travel Trends we've seen going into 2025
and and if if you talk just about 2024
um for December itself we've seen the
top searches for people Indian Travelers
wanting to travel have been Goa bagdogra
Kochi Dubai and almati these are the
destination for December my God I'm
already getting major foro moit because
of all the trends that you described
from the cherry blossoms to the northern
lights and so on and so forth to the
wellness retreats we want to do them all
right actually not one we want to do as
many as possible in every given year but
then B budgets are finite so we have to
work with what we have I'll come back on
some of the individual Trends in in just
a bit but Priya you tell us now clearly
all this is happening but what about
from when you see it through a financial
lens has it meant uh You Know Better
Business for you as well when it comes
to the travel insurance segment
absolutely and um you know quite frankly
I'm quite fascinated to hear what moit
said and you know you have an example in
me who's traveled to Japan just for the
cherry blossoms and uh it's amazing to
see what's happening across the globe
and how the travel Trends and tourism is
coming back we have around 15 million uh
Indian Nationals who have traveled in
the first half of 2024 and we expect um
you know total 80 um you know million uh
traveling throughout the year of 20124
so the travel uh trend is back uh we did
see some slow down uh during the covid
season postco it has come back with
great um you know amazing progress and
alongside the travel season and people
going for experiential uh you know kind
of uh travel uh destinations and all the
you know fancy names that M mentioned uh
even the insurance sector the financial
insurance sector has moved that along
the side in the curve of how people have
chosen destinations and travel uh you
know kind of uh planning and it's it's
really uh fascinating to see how the
growth has happened is uh a kager of
around 14% that we've observed and uh by
20 2040 uh we're seeing a you know
explosive growth of almost 50% of the
total travel tourism Insurance uh that's
going to come our way so the travel
insurance industry seems to be growing
at these big numbers 40 50% because of
the the Boom in travel it's a reflection
of how people are choosing uh to travel
U uh internationally as well as
domestically so Priya I mean just a
question on um the trends from this year
now travel insurance tends to be a very
minuscule percentage of the overall trip
cost right probably 00 1% uh so in terms
of the premium Trends in 24 what have we
seen so far are premiums going up going
down what should we expect well um you
know when you talk about a travel
product uh you know while it's a
minuscule of the cost of the total
travel planning that a consumer would do
uh it will all depend on the you know
country the duration of stay uh you know
what kind of um you know stay plan that
you have and you know features of you
know are you going for a Adventure Sport
kind of an activity so it will all
depend on that but with the growing
volume of uh business and uh the way the
penetration is increasing and more and
more people are being aware because of
two reasons one uh the treatment cost U
me locations or you know destinations
that people are traveling as well as you
know the Peace of Mind typically um you
know 50,000 USD some insured for a aged
uh uh customer of around 50 years would
uh the premium would range around uh
10,000 odd rupees for a gold plan and a
more comprehensive and very very uh uh
you know all-inclusive program would
cost around 15,000 odd so that's quite
uh the range in which you would see the
um you know travel insurance products
being fair enough so so they're not sort
of shooting through the roof we're not
expecting a very huge surge in travel
premiums right that's good to hear I'll
come back on it in in just a bit but
moit again to talk about the trends and
the costing part uh now people are
traveling irrespective of the cost but
the fact is that costs are going up
right you look at flights to Europe in
throughout 2024 I remember I mean preo I
took a flight to one of my dream
destinations in Europe for some you know
50k for a return return ticket and now
that number is going to what 75,000
880,000 so in terms of just cost for
this uh this sort of international
travel what are we in for in
2025 yeah it's a really good point um
cost of living is still top of mind for
Indian Travelers like um Indian
Travelers prioritize the cost of flights
cost of hotels even the cost of food of
the destination that they're going for
but having said that the rising middle
class and the increase in travel spend
that individuals have now and also Visa
access becoming um slightly easier in
many of the locations continues to to
drive the interest among Indian
Travelers an interesting fact we also
found out was 66% of Indian Travelers
are planning to travel more in 2025 so
that shows that although cost is top of
mind they want to continue to travel
into the new year and having said that
what we are seeing is um Airlines
increasing their networks um there's a
lot of like domestic there's a lot of
low value lowc cost Airlines having
competition and because of this
additional networks to different
destination what we'll see in 2025 is
the prices stabilizing further and and
and to meet the demand of uh of Indian
Travelers we expect more routs to to
start beginning which will also
stabilize the prices further that sounds
really good actually you know what um M
we're playing a graphic right now from
your report that uh highlights some of
the maybe most wallet friendly or budget
friendly destinations for 2025 yeah
we've got them on the screen now Oslo
London Doha uh there's Soul there's Baku
where there's a slight drop and there's
kazakistan where there's a big drop
actually 44% drop in airfares can you
tell us a little more about it I mean
this is what average of how many months
and can we project this into the new
year we all want to believe that yes
airfares are not going to go through the
roof so what are the destinations to
look at yeah those numbers are very
exciting for us as well that is why we
wanted to highlight them to our Indian
Travelers like seeing almati and
kazakistan having that 44% reduction in
price year on year over 12 months um is
really exciting because uh it shows that
Indian Travelers want to go and
experience the culture which takes back
to to the point I mentioned about
cultural exploration it's also about
going to destinations which are more
pocket friendly and stronger rupee plays
uh quite important um in in in this and
and we also see the the Visa access
which is becoming easier for Indians to
traveling to these destinations and
because of that the airlines are having
more networks um to these roots and
because of that we see the average fair
prices dropping significantly ly and you
see almati in kazakistan known for his
culture and and and and really good
Landscapes we also saw um Jakarta in
Indonesia which is which is a wellness
Retreat we see some some really stunning
beaches there as well same with
Singapore it's getting popular um every
year because of what it offers to the
Indian
Travelers very very interesting so M
before we let you go uh you know give us
more hope I you guys have done a top
destinations list as well I think and I
was very proud to I think shalong
features on that list of top
destinations of 2025 right so tell us
how you compile that list and uh you
know any hacks any tips for better
planning more sort of budget friendly
planning how can we have happier
holidays in
2025 yeah I was really excited to see um
shilong as the number one destination
for Indian Travelers in terms of
searches so what we saw in terms of the
the data crunching we did was um which
destination has seen an increase in
searches compared to the previous year
and shilong saw a tremendous increase of
over
800% um for Indian Travelers um shilong
also known as the the Scotland of the
East um pristine legs beautiful
landscapes easy access obviously no Visa
issues for us Indian Travelers so I
wasn't surprised to finally have an
Indian city on that list Baku continues
to be um really strong in the top 10 at
number two um which gives you an
affordable European experience and easy
to get to as well and easy Visa access
um tromo in Norway also makes the top 10
of the list which is known for going
seeing Northern Lights and Aurora
boreales and then you can see tashkin in
usbekistan also known for his culture
and and Beauty that's drawing Indian
Travelers so these are uh the different
uh destinations we've seen based on what
Indian Travelers have been searching on
the Skyscanner website and app so how
many of them have you covered moit and
which ones are you heading to in the New
Year definitely tashkin in usbekistan is
on my U goto list for sure uh
unfortunately I haven't been to shilong
as well so shilong should be there in my
number one list as well so can't wait to
cover both shilong and tashen very soon
fantastic well we wish you good luck
with that plan and thank you very much
for joining in this gives us plenty of
food for thought and uh you know plenty
to think and plan about and get excited
about in the New Year travel always top
of mine thank you very much for giving
us The Skys scanner
perspective thank you so much all right
well with that we have to take a very
quick break we'll come back on the other
side and now that we know which are the
hottest destinations to get to the
question is you need to pay a lot of
focus and attention to the travel
insurance part it's more than just a
quick checklist before you're heading to
the airport we'll tell you why uh priia
will give us more details on this in
just a bit
[Music]
let's talk
money welcome back here with us on let's
talk money and this week it's all about
travel how to plan better plan smarter
and how to ensure that you have the
right kind of travel insurance as you're
rushing out towards the airport Priya
deshmuk is with us in the studios she's
from ICS Lomar and she's helping us
understand all the nitties of a travel
policy typically I admit this is the
last thing people sort of look into
which is why we're here to ask the
questions prya so what all does a travel
policy cover I should know beforehand
right rather than Landing up in a in a
problem outside and then figuring out
okay does my policy AB have this or not
AB absolutely one of the surveys by
Global Travel U Trends report 50% of
people travel you know book their
tickets 14 days in advance and almost
similar numbers was buy insurance in the
last two days of the travel that's
planned for so it's very much of a last
minute kind of a uh you know Affair but
it's very critical for people to
understand that the country that they're
visiting what is the kind of healthare
system how are things and in order to
really avoid the last minute you know
hassle or any issue that is caused
because of any medical emergency or
non-medical uh you know situations of
loss of baggage or mugging or any kind
of other mishaps it's important to
really buy
what all your insurance plans really
covers so does the insurance plan cover
something like mugging as well yes yes
yes I mean uh almost um you know 30% of
Indians that take trips uh there is a
situation where uh they have had uh
issue with mugging any fraudulent
payment other challenges I mean those
are common issues that Travelers really
experience um there are um you know
instances where people get tricked so
all of these elements are covered as
part of uh non-medical coverage in the
insurance travel insurance plan so you
have the basic critical you know vanila
offering of medical insurance any kind
of emergency any hospitalization for
that matter any kind of personal
accident but at the same time you have
loss of baggage loss of passport you
know all those kind of issues also
covered as part of the offering so are
these plans fairly standardized across
the industry or do you have to be very
careful and go through all the
conditions because maybe IC Lombard is
offering maybe someone else is is not uh
so the reason I'm asking is that you
know we don't typically pay so much
attention to what all is covered see the
zest of travel and most of most of the
travel is either for leisure or study or
maybe work related travel people tend to
really uh miss out and pay as much
attention that one would uh need for a
travel insurance plan and the travel
insurance plan would uh choice would
essentially depend on the destination as
I said uh what kind of uh long stay or a
short stay what is a family combination
that is traveling and what is the
infrastructure in the city uh what are
the local uh you know uh situations or
scenarios that are going to impact
either health or uh you know non-health
kind of situations that the traveler May
face and hence it's extremely important
to go through the details of what your
policy covers what are the critical U
exclusion lists and also be familiarized
as to if at all there is a claim to be
made what are the processes to really go
through uh you know if one has to go
through that you know scenario or
situation no absolutely so that which is
why I was asking that all the things
that you you kind of listed out which is
a medical emergency which is a
non-medical emergency which could be
loss of baggage which could be things
like you know mugging or theft or you
know loss of documents do most insurers
in the average travel insurance policy
do do most insurers cover this so uh
there's something called as basic cover
and uh now New Age products cover
multiple other uh features so there is a
bare minimum medical emergency and loss
of maggage kind of feature okay uh
however there are a lot of novelty kind
of features that have been added by New
Age insurance companies like ourselves
so you have Adventure Sport you have
Visa Service uh so you apply for a Visa
your Visa get rejected so your insurance
covers the entire processing fee uh so
that's something new uh you know
adventure sports was always excluded but
uh now it's all about experiential uh
you know traveling and it's important
for you to really have that assurance
and that you know security so uh there
are plants which are very very
customizable they can be personalized
depending on the need for your travel
the stay uh the uh number of days that
you're staying in a particular country
uh the requirement that's there so the
newer plants the new age plants do have
customization options available and it
would have impact on uh your coverages
as well as the cost of travel insurance
premium that you would so got that for
now to go back to the example that you
gave earlier about 50-year-old traveling
to any International destination right
uh you said the cover there would be
around
10,700 but that's for a 180 days of
foreign stay correct correct that's
right I mean that's a long stay uh you
could have programs where you're going
for for a Leisure trip weeks two weeks
or all uh so you have a different kind
of uh premium which is much much uh you
know kind of uh uh smaller compared to
what I mentioned and uh depending on the
country that you're going it would again
differ and and uh the premiums are
really really very economic even even
for something like Adventure Sports and
all the funky Stu there's a little bit
of layer of uh you know risk out there
and you load up as an insurer you would
load up the premium but uh still it
would be much much cheaper Ball Park
estimates say a 2 3 week trip the basic
cover which includes your you know
medical emergency loss of baggage and
throw in that Adventure cover so how
much would it 6,000 to 7,000 range is
the premium that you would have for a 2
we uh you know uh travel and some of
these add-ons that are you know kind of
I mentioned just now would be the
ballbar number okay Priya so that's
really helpful finally now Summit all up
for us what are the things that we
should check read ask before buying
travel insurance um you know as we
discussed throughout um you know travel
insurance is one of the most important
and core um uh you know requirement one
when somebody is traveling either for
leisure or business or any kind of tour
and the last thing you want is to be
stuck by any kind of a situation and get
caught in the middle of a problem uh
having said that um you know in travel
insurances to give you Assurance peace
of mind uh one must check uh what are
the exclusions and inclusions depending
on the you know what kind of coverage do
you have what country you're traveling
if you're traveling to a country like a
um you know us or Europe or any other
country having high amount of um you
know medical expenses when it comes to
medical emergencies you got to really
make sure that you have adequate some
insured uh check the start date and end
date U of your travel insurance policy
depending on the travel dates that
you're traveling also also the
geographical scope in terms of coverages
restrictions and exclusions and uh
familiarize yourself with the claim
process and depending on your
requirement and need U you know uh
certain add-on uh New Age covers that
are there whether it is sports uh and
Adventure car rentals you know we've
seen almost 20% of people who travel
abroad now prefer to have U you know
rental cars uh so to cover uh that bit
of any kind of damage or any mishap you
have insurance cover Adon so such kind
of add-on covers align to your itery on
uh your leisure and the trip that you're
planning you have to really make sure
that all of that is kind of concerted
and kind of aligned with your plan Priya
that's a really important point and
before we go we must ask you in the
event of a mishap something gets lost
you lose your phone you lose your
documents God forbid a medical emergency
what's the the process what do you do
you call back to India how how does the
claim happen explain the process so for
in case of a u you know non- medical
emergency like a flight gets cancelled
or there is a baggage loss so we have a
auto tracking mechanism and autoc claim
reimbursement or uh you know kind of
payoff to the consumer so it's
completely hassle-free the last last
thing we want our Travelers or you know
insur members to really worry about how
do you claim in case of travel being
canceled because of trip cancellation
which is very will uh you know available
as a information and we have integration
to really get that info transmitted uh
similarly talking about uh uh you know
medical emergency we have our partners
across the globe uh you know there are
plants worldwide cover there are certain
geographical uh specific uh you know
plants that you uh buy we have uh a
clearly mentioned U you know phone line
number our application Sor yeah we have
an application where in the consumer can
go in and and uh just dial that uh you
know uh uh toll-free number connect with
a partner and the whole end to end
handholding of the whole process will be
taken care by a partner so this is a
24x7 um you know facility that is
available in case of emergency any kind
of uh you know kind of uh uh
transmission from or other any kind of
Transit that has to be arranged from one
location to another if there is an
accident uh a person has to be moved
from that particular location of an
accident to the nearest facility all of
that ambulance services and any kind of
uh support uh to offer all of that is
being managed by our and how quick is
this is emergency response and uh in
case of emergency it would uh range
anywhere between 30 minutes to 2 hours
depending on the criticality of the
situation so we have Partnerships across
the globe uh whether it is Hospital
partnership or you know any other
network partnership those are in place
for us to support our customers very
very reassuring to hear but hopefully we
we don't you know need those uh Services
when we travel but all always good to be
secured know that you're covered in case
of any eventuality PR very very helpful
conversation thank you very much it was
a pleasure thank you very much wish you
a fabulous 2025 more travel more joy and
more secure trips ahead thank you all
right with that it's a wrap on this
week's edition of let's talk money thank
you for watching we'll see you again
with the Final Countdown the final
episode of 2024 coming up next week
[Music]
let's talk money